We are working with a list of state capitals
that we could use in a quiz-like game.
Let’s see some list operations we can apply
to the list, specifically operations that
add items to the list and operations that
remove items from the list.
As we go through each built-in method used
to affect a list, we should pay close attention
to the differences among these methods.
To start, I have three state capitals added
to the 126-list_operations file for the first
three states in the United States alphabetically,
on line 1.
I want to add Sacramento to the list next.
I will, on line 2, add this statement: capitals.append(“Sacramento”)
to add the capital of California to the list.
Then, with a print statement for the capitals
variable already in place on line 4, I will
run this code.
The list prints as expected.
Here is a general programming note: in programming,
a period (.) serves as the "accessor" that
allows you to reach into an object and use
one of its methods.
Think of it like opening a toolbox to use
a specific tool.
For example, in capitals.append(), capitals
is the object (or "toolbox") and append is
the method (or "tool").
The period is the mechanism that lets you
access the append method specifically from
the capitals object.
Therefore, methods are functions that are
tied to a specific object and are invoked
using this period notation.
Whereas append adds an item to the end of
a list, the insert method inserts an item
at a specified position.
In adding capital cities to our list, I forgot
that Arkansas and its capital, Little Rock,
must be inserted before Sacramento.
Using the zero-based positioning Python has,
I want Little Rock to be the fourth capital,
so I will insert this text into position three.
I will add a line after the append statement
and type: capitals.insert(3, “LittleRock”).
I will rerun the code.
So far, all these list operations are working
perfectly.
Next, let’s see how to change the value
of a list item.
I forgot to put a space between Little and
Rock, so I want to change that capital.
Little Rock is at position 3 in the list,
so I will move to line 5 in the code and type
capitals[3] = “Little Rock” with a space,
to make that change.
Then, using the print(capitals) statement
on line 6, I will run this code, and see the
updated list.
Let’s now look at two ways we can remove
items from a list.
First, we can remove an item by value.
I will add a statement on line 4 with this
text: capitals.remove(“Juneau”).
Let’s rerun this code.
We have a problem now, don’t we?
Little Rock is on the list twice, and Sacramento
is no longer there.
Why is that?
Take a moment to do the first part of the
Review 1.2 exercise in the workbook to determine
why you think this happened, and then in the
next video, we will solve this problem and
continue with these list operations.